Finding Aid for Oratorical Association (University of Michigan) records, 1890-1961
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Oratorical Association (University of Michigan) records 1890-1961
University of Michigan. Oratorical Association.
87286 Bimu F21 2
Constitutions, minutes, correspondence, lecturers' files, and publicity material; include correspondence, 1890-1896, of Thomas C. Trueblood and James B. Angell relating to the establishment of the association
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Mrs. Lucille Upham (Donor No. 3799 ) in 1961 and 1962. Additional files came from a storage room in the University's Administration Building in 1984. The provenance of this last accession is not certain.
No further additions to the records expected.
The records are open without restriction.
The University of Michigan Oratorical Association was formally initiated in 1912, although the tradition of bringing lecturers to speak on campus had been long established. As early as 1824, the University was visited by itinerant speakers, and in 1854 the Student Lecture Association was formed. As its name suggests, this was a student-run organization whose purpose was to bring lecturers to the University. This was in contrast to the faculty-sponsored Oratorical Association, organized by Professor-Emeritus Thomas Trueblood in 1889. The latter organization was essentially a debating society, but it took on the form and function of the Student Lecture Association when that group went bankrupt in 1912.
The lectures themselves covered a broad spectrum of interests. Some of the early speakers included Horace Greeley, Victoria Woodhull, Mark Twain, and P.T. Barnum. Later speakers, such as Eleanor Roosevelt, Admiral Byrd, Margaret Bourke-White and Ogden Nash continued this tradition of widely varied lecture topics. Some spoke on serious political issues of the day, or important scientific discoveries, while still others simply entertained.
By the early 1960s, however, interest in the lecture series had waned. At some point in time, probably around 1961, the Oratorical Association quietly collapsed, due to lack of interest.
The papers of the University of Michigan Oratorical Association consist of nearly three linear feet of material. The collection is organized in five series: History, Minutes, Correspondence, Name File and Publicity
The uses of this collection are rather limited. Probably only researchers of the University of Michigan's history will find it of any value. Even then, the quality of the material here is low, consisting as it does primarily of newspaper clippings which are readily obtainable elsewhere. Although the Oratorical Association made use of many notable figures of the day, neither the Correspondence nor the Name-file yield unique information about these people. Possibly the only thing this collection reflects is the changing public taste in entertainment.
Subjects:
Lectures and lecturing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Oratorical Association.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Trueblood, Thomas C. (Thomas Clarkson), 1856-1951.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Oratorical Association.; Public speaking.; Debates--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Lecture notes.; Photographs.
- History
  The series History documents the life of the organization in a rather sketchy fashion. This small series is divided into a "general" section, "Applications for Lectures," "Centennial" (of the University of Michigan), "Constitutions," and "Lists of Lectures." The latter gives listings as early as 1855.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Applications for lectures (Box 1)
  - Centennial (University of Michigan) (Box 1)
  - Constitutions 1910-1916 (Box 1)
  - Lists of Lectures 1855-1897 (Box 1)
- Minutes
  Minutes is probably the most intriguing series in the collection. it covers the years 1916-1934, and better than any other material shows the workings of the Oratorical Association itself.
  - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1928 (Box 1)
  - 1928-1935 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The third series is Correspondence, which is somewhat larger than History. The series is arranged chronologically, and spans the years 1890-1961. Most of the correspondence concerns the detail of arranging for speakers to come to the University, negotiations with agents, and so forth.
  - 1890-1921 (Box 1)
  - 1927-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1961 (Box 1)
- Name File
  The fourth series, the Name File, is easily the largest in the collection. Arranged alphabetically, the series consists of files on the various speakers and performers who were part of the Oratorical Association's lecture series. Each file consists primarily of newspaper clippings advertising or reporting on the lectures and performances. The time span covered is roughly 1939-1960.
  - Adamic, Louis (Box 1)
  - Agar, Herbert (Box 1)
  - Aherne, Brian (Box 1)
  - Allen, Jay (Box 1)
  - Arnall, Ellis (Box 1)
  - Atlee, Clement (Box 1)
  - Atwater, Edith--Dekker, Albert (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Hanson (Box 1)
  - Barkley, Alben (Box 1)
  - Beebe, William (Box 1)
  - Bing, Rudolph (Box 1)
  - Bourke-White, Margaret (Box 1)
  - Bolitho, Hector (Box 1)
  - Bowles, Chester (Box 1)
  - Bricker, John W--Gore, Albert (Box 1)
  - Brown, Cecil (Box 1)
  - Brown, John Mason (Box 1)
  - Brownell, Herbert (Box 1)
  - Bryan, Julien (Box 1)
  - Bunche, Ralph (Box 1)
  - Byrd, Richard E. (Box 1)
  - Caine Mutiny (Box 1)
  - Cartier, Jacques (Box 1)
  - Cerf, Bennett (Box 1)
  - Chapman, Wendell (Box 1)
  - Chase, Ilka (Box 1)
  - Chatterton, Ruth (Box 1)
  - Childs, Marquis (Box 1)
  - Churchill, Randolph (Box 1)
  - Clapper, Olive (Mrs. Raymond) (Box 1)
  - Clark, Mark (Box 1)
  - Clemenceau, Pierce (Box 1)
  - Cousins, Norman (Box 1)
  - Craig, John D. (Box 1)
  - Curie, Eve (Box 1)
  - Davis, Bette--Merrill, Gary (Box 2)
  - De Madariaga, Salvador (Box 2)
  - De Mille, Agnes (Box 2)
  - Don Juan In Hell (Box 2)
  - Dos Passos, John (Box 2)
  - Douglas, Helen Gahagan (Box 2)
  - Douglas, Paul (Box 2)
  - Douglas, Paul--Judd, Walter H. (Box 2)
  - Douglas, William 0. (Box 2)
  - Dowling, Eddie (Box 2)
  - Draper, Ruth (Box 2)
  - Drummond, Roscoe (Box 2)
  - Duranty, Walter (Box 2)
  - Eliot, George Fielding (Box 2)
  - Evans, Maurice (Box 2)
  - Fadiman, Clifton (Box 2)
  - Felix (Archduke) (Box 2)
  - Fischer, Louis (Box 2)
  - Fisher, Joe (Box 2)
  - Forman, Harrison (Box 2)
  - Garden, Mary (Box 2)
  - Gibson, Hugh (Box 2)
  - Gielgud, Sir John (Box 2)
  - Gish, Lillian (Box 2)
  - Glubb, Sir John (Box 2)
  - Grenfell, Joyce (Box 2)
  - Hambro, Carl (Box 2)
  - Heiser, Victor (Box 2)
  - Henry, Taylor (Box 2)
  - Hindus, Maurice (Box 2)
  - Holbrook, Hal (Mark Twain) (Box 2)
  - Holmes, Burton 1956 (Box 2)
  - Holmes, Burton 1961 (Box 2)
  - Hull, Henry (Box 2)
  - Humphrey, Hubert-Morton, Thurston B. (Box 2)
  - Janeway, Eliot (Box 2)
  - Jessel, George (Box 2)
  - John Brown's Body (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Osa (Box 2)
  - Kaltenborn, H.V. (Box 2)
  - Kefauver, Estes (Box 2)
  - Kirk, Lydia (Box 2)
  - Knickerbocker, H.R. (Box 2)
  - Knight, C.W.R. (Box 2)
  - La Follette, Philip (Box 2)
  - Lane, Arthur Bliss (Box 2)
  - Larson, Arthur (Box 2)
  - Lattimore, Owen (Box 2)
  - Laughton, Charles (Box 2)
  - Lawrence, William (Box 2)
  - Lawes, Lewis (Box 2)
  - Lewis, Fulton (Jr.) (Box 2)
  - Lewis, Sinclair--Browne, Lewis (Box 2)
  - Lie, Trygve (Box 2)
  - Lilienthal, David E. (Box 2)
  - Limb, Ben (Box 2)
  - Lochner, Louis (Box 2)
  - Lockhart, R. Bruce (Box 2)
  - McClintic, Guthrie (Box 2)
  - McCormick, Anne O'Hare (Box 2)
  - Magidoff, Robert (Box 2)
  - Mann, Thomas (Box 2)
  - Marceau, Marcel (Box 2)
  - Masaryk, Jan (Box 2)
  - Meredith, Burgess (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, Ruth (Box 2)
  - Moorehead, Agnes (Box 2)
  - Mowrer, Edgar Ansel (Box 2)
  - Nash, Ogden (Box 2)
  - Nutting, Anthony (Box 2)
  - Pandit, Mme. Vijaya (Box 2)
  - Peale, Norman Vincent (Box 2)
  - Pearson, Drew (Box 2)
  - Perkins, Frances (Box 2)
  - Priest, Ivy Baker (Box 2)
  - Purvis, Melvin (Box 2)
  - Quiz Kids (Box 2)
  - Raiguel, George E. (Box 2)
  - Rains, Claude (Box 2)
  - Romey, Roger (Box 2)
  - Rathbone, Basil (Box 2)
  - Reston, Janes (Box 2)
  - Reynolds, Quentin (Box 2)
  - Rivalry (The) (Box 2)
  - Robeson, Mrs. Paul (Box 2)
  - Rogers, Will (Jr.) (Box 2)
  - Romulo, Carlos (Box 2)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 2)
  - St. Denis, Ruth (Box 3)
  - Sayre, Francis (Box 3)
  - Schenck, Earl (Box 3)
  - Schwartz, Harry (Box 3)
  - Shrimer, Herb (Box 3)
  - Skinner, Cornelia Otia (Box 3)
  - Smith, Nicol (Box 3)
  - Spaak, Paul (Box 3)
  - Steinbeck (John) drama (Box 3)
  - Stewart-Roddie, W. (Box 3)
  - Stirling, Yates, Jr. (Box 3)
  - Stowe, Leland (Box 3)
  - Swing, Raymond Gram (Box 3)
  - Thaw, Lawrence (Box 3)
  - Thomas, Lowell (Jr.) (Box 3)
  - Thompson, Dorothy (Box 3)
  - Tompkins, Warwick (Box 3)
  - Untermeyer, Louis (Box 3)
  - Valtin, Jan (Box 3)
  - Villiers, Alan (Box 3)
  - Van Zeeland, Paul (Box 3)
  - Ward, Barbara (Box 3)
  - Webster, Margret (Box 3)
  - Wedemeyer, Albert C. (Box 3)
  - Wei, Tao-Ming (Box 3)
  - Wells, Sumner (Box 3)
  - Werner, Max (Box 3)
  - West, Rebecca (Box 3)
  - Wiley, Alexander--Morse, Wayne (Box 3)
  - Williams, Evelyn (Box 3)
  - Wolfit, Donald (Box 3)
  - Woollcott, Alexander (Box 3)
  - World Affairs Council (Box 3)
  - World of Carl Sandburg (Box 3)
  - Wright, Richard (Box 3)
  - Yarnell, H.E. (Box 3)
  - Ybarra, T.R. (Box 3)
- Publicity
  The Publicity series in some ways mirrors the contents of the Name File. However, it is arranged chronologically, and while it too is mainly Made up of newspaper clippings, these usually deal with the entire lecture series of a given year rather than with individual performances. It documents the years 1926-1961 with only a couple of gaps in the sequence.
  - 1926-1939 (Box 3)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 3)
  - 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes pictures of he Oratorical Board and of debating teams whose activities were administered under the auspices of the Oratorical Association.
  - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 3)